Guide to the Beekman Family Papers 1720-1920's MS 51
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
- Box 35(A), Estate Papers, 1763-1839
  - William Beekman, James Beekman, Receipts and Accounts, 1791-1819 (Box 35(A), Folder 3)
  - Reverend Abraham Keteltas, Estate Papers, 1781-1802 (Box 35(A), Folder 4)
  - Gerard Beekman, Accounts, 1768-1780 (Box 35(A), Folder 5)
  - James Beekman, John Beekman, William Beekman, Samuel Beekman, Accounts, Letters, Receipts, 1782-1811 (Box 35(A), Folder 6)
  - John Beekman, Accounts, Letters, Receipts, 1792-1798 (Box 35(A), Folder 7)
  - Gerard Beekman and Reverend Abraham Keteltas, Estate Inventories, Statements of Rents and Lots, 1793-1836 (Box 35(A), Folder 8)
- Box 35(B), Estate Papers, 1731-1812
  For description of materials, see White's guide, Volume 2, pages 309-310.
  - William Beekman, Eighteenth-Century Deeds, 1731, 1785 (Box 35(B), Folder 9)
  - James Beekman, John Beekman, Real Estate Papers, 1808-1812 (Box 35(B), Folder 10)
  - Beekman Family, Estate and Account Book, October 1795 (Box 35(B), Folder 11)
  - William Beekman, Estate, Account Book, 1731-1802 (Box 35(B), Folder 12)
  - Beekman Family, Estate Book, 1795-1806 (Box 35(B), Folder 13)
  - William Beekman, Deceased October 8, 1795, Estate Book, 1803-1812 (Box 35(B), Folder 14)
    Description of contents in White's guide, Volume 2, P. 310.
  - William Beekman, Uncle William Beekman, Estate Books and Negatives (Photostat Copies) of Family Estate Book, 1795-1812 (Box 35(B), Folder 15)
- Box 36, Legal Documents, 1707-1822
  For folder descriptions, see White's guide, Volume 2, page 311. Additionally, this folder contains a small amount of miscellaneous material not directly pertaining to legal documentation, including sermons and parlor games.
  - William and Gerard Beekman, Deeds, Bills, Receipts and Agreements, including one letter in French, 1707-1788 (Box 36, Folder 1)
  - Abraham Beekman, Samuel Beekman, James Beekman, Gerard Beekman, Indentures, 1718-1818 (Box 36, Folder 2)
  - Indentures, 1742-1763 (Box 36, Folder 3)
  - William Beekman, Abraham Beekman, Gerard Beekman, Mary Beekman, Catherine Beekman, Indentures, Bulk, 1795-1822; 1774-1822 (Box 36, Folder 4)
  - John Beekman, Gerard Beekman, Peter Taylor, Indentures, 1761-1818 (Box 36, Folder 5)
  - William and Gerard Beekman, Indentures, Release for Water Lot, 1751-1792 (Box 36, Folder 6)
- Box 37 and 38(A), Beekman Family Estates, Accounts and Correspondence; Box 38(A), James W. Beekman, 1761-1863
  Boxes 37 and 38(A) have been combined into one box. For more information, see White's guide, Volume 2, pages 312-319.
  - William Beekman, Materials Pertaining to Estate Division, Funeral Costs, Accounts, and Federal Repayment for Revolutionary War Cannons. Includes William Beekman's Estate Inventory, Negatives and Original, 1764-1795 (Box 37, Folder 1)
  - Gerard Beekman, James Beekman, Samuel Beekman, Abraham Beekman, Mary Beekman, Agreements, Indentures, and Correspondence, 1764-1813 (Box 37, Folder 2)
  - James Beekman, William Beekman, Mary Beekman, Cornelia Beekman, and Gerard Beekman, Bills, Receipts, Correspondence. Includes Promissory Note Sent from William Duer to John Pintard, 1792., 1757-1796 (Box 37, Folder 3)
  - Abraham Van Gelder and Daniel Ryan, Estate Documents, Power of Attorney, Receipts, and Indentures, 1765-1820 (Box 37, Folder 4)
  - Jane Keteltas Estate Documents, Receipts and Accounts for Gerard Beekman, John Beekman, James Beekman, 1767-1823 (Box 37, Folder 5)
  - James W. Beekman, Accounts with John Beekman, The Heirs of William Beekman, J.C.D. Beekman, and Abraham Cox, 1820-1842 (Box 38(A), Folder 1)
  - James W. Beekman, Correspondence from Seeland and Beckwith, 1838-1849 (Box 38(A), Folder 2)
  - James W. Beekman, Estate, Property Documentation Pertaining to Beekmantown, Circa 1830s-1850s (Box 38(A), Folder 3)
    Materials are not organized in chronological order.
  - James W. Beekman, Accounts and Items Pertaining to California Trade, Bill of Goods for W.J. Milledoler, Circa 1840s-1863 (Box 38(A), Folder 4)
- Box 38(B), James W. Beekman, 1823-1897
  - James W. Beekman, Mount Pleasant Dutch Reformed Church, 1860-1861 (Box 38(B), Folder 5)
  - James W. Beekman, Taxes, Assessments, 1855-1858, undated (Box 38(B), Folder 6)
  - James W. Beekman, Correspondence, Accounts (some with London), Obituary, Clippings, American Tract Society Document, Will of Alida Beekman, Fr/Ger ad for Water of Cologne, some genealogical research, 1823-1897 (Box 38(B), Folder 7)
  - James W. Beekman, Accounts, Mortgages, Assessments, Taxes, 1837-1855 (Box 38(B), Folder 8)
  - James W. Beekman, Receipts, 1856-1857 (Box 38(B), Folder 9)
  - James W. Beekman, Accounts, Receipts, 1858 (Box 38(B), Folder 10)
  - James W. Beekman, Accounts, Receipts, 1859 (Box 38(B), Folder 11)
  - James W. Beekman, Lecture on Divorce, Proposal for "The Three Hundred" Patriotic Social Club, Undated (Box 38(B), Folder 12)
- Box 39(A), Genealogical Papers, Circa 1870-1903
  For extensive detail regarding the contents of this box, see White's guide, Volume 2, pages 328-335 (Note: Materials within Box 39(A) and 39(B) appear to have been compiled by J.W. Beekman, Jr., for use in a publication; it's possible that the June 15, 1908 New York Evening Post article in Box 12, Folder 2, is the result of this research). For further genealogical material, see Box 12.
  - Organizational Material and Correspondence Pertaining to the Society of Colonial Wars, Yacht Club, New-York Historical Society, Columbia Alumni Association, Union Club, and Trustee of New York Hospital, Lake George Memorial, 1903, undated (Box 39(A), Folder 1)
  - Genealogical Material (collected in the 1890's), Including Material Copied from Family Bibles, Copy of 1700's Peartree Patent, Correspondence, Family Trees., 1870-1890, undated (Box 39(A), Folder 2)
  - Genealogical Material, including Family Trees, Rutgers/Depeyster Families, Issue of Jan. 1903 Huguenot Magazine., 1893-1894, undated (Box 39(A), Folder 3)
  - Genealogical Material, Predominantly Correspondence, Some in German and French, 1874-1901, undated (Box 39(A), Folder 4)
  - Genealogical Material, Correspondence, Copies of Dutch Reformed Church Records, List of Marriages, Newspaper Clippings, Some in French, 1892-1899 (Box 39(A), Folder 5)
  - Genealogical Material, Mostly Focused on pre-Colonial Dutch Ancestry, Notes and Drafts of Family Trees, Correspondence, Correspondence, Some in French One in Dutch (translated), 1892-1896, undated (Box 39(A), Folder 6)
- Box 39(B), Genealogical Papers, 1880-1901
  In the majority of these folders, there are documents in Dutch and French.
  - Genealogical Material, Much in Dutch, Will of Cornelius Beekman, Circa 1755-1795 (Box 39(B), Folder 7)
    Many materials are in fragile condition or placed within plastic sleeves.
  - Genealogical Material, Notes, Some in French, Dutch, 1890-1900 (Box 39(B), Folder 8)
  - Genealogical Material, Notes, Newspaper Article on Beekman Family From the New York Evening Post, dated June 15, 1901, Advertisements for Genealogy Books, Some in French, 1895-1901, undated (Box 39(B), Folder 9)
  - Genealogical Material, Notes, Correspondence, Livingston Family Tree, Some in Dutch and French, 1880-1890, undated (Box 39(B), Folder 10)
  - Genealogical Material, Notes, Correspondence, Some in French, 1892-1901, undated (Box 39(B), Folder 11)
  - Genealogical Material, Notes, Correspondence, Order Forms for Genealogy Books, Some in Dutch, 1896-1900 (Box 39(B), Folder 12)
  - Genealogical Material, Notes, Correspondence, 1894-1896, undated (Box 39(B), Folder 13)
  - Genealogical Material, Notes, Correspondence, Documentation Pertaining to Marriages of Morris and Walton Families, Morris Family History, 1885-1896, undated (Box 39(B), Folder 14)
  - Genealogical Material, Pertaining to the Death of Sir Elias Beekman (1678), Battle of Aardenburg, and the Beekman Coat of Arms, Some in Dutch, French, 1894-1897, undated (Box 39(B), Folder 15)
- Box 40(A), Genealogical Papers, Undated
  Some additional description available in White's guide, Volume 2, page 336.
  - General Family History, Notes, Undated (Box 40(A), Folder 1)
  - Documentation Regarding European Beekmans, Notes and Correspondence, Undated, 1893-1899 (Box 40(A), Folder 2)
  - William Beekman, Miscellaneous Beekman, Notes, Family Tree, Newspaper Clippings, Undated (Box 40(A), Folder 3)
  - Livingston Family, Undated (Box 40(A), Folder 4)
  - Materials Pertaining to Related Families, Including Duane, Stuyvesant, Abeel, DeBow, and Others, Undated (Box 40(A), Folder 5)
  - Material Pertaining to Mount Pleasant, Undated (Box 40(A), Folder 6)
  - Drew Family, Undated (Box 40(A), Folder 7)
  - G.W. Beekman, Undated (Box 40(A), Folder 8)
  - Gerard Beekman (Father of J.W. Beekman), Undated (Box 40(A), Folder 9)
  - Gerardus Beekman, Undated (Box 40(A), Folder 10)
  - Col. Henry Beekman, Undated (Box 40(A), Folder 11)
  - Jacobus Beekman, Undated (Box 40(A), Folder 12)
  - James Beekman, Undated (Box 40(A), Folder 13)
  - Keteltas Family, Undated (Box 40(A), Folder 15)
- Box 40(B), Genealogical Papers, 1893-1894, undated
  - Dr. William Beekman, Undated (Box 40(B), Folder 16)
  - Other Beekman Branches, Undated (Box 40(B), Folder 17)
  - Notebook of Genealogy, Undated (Box 40(B), Folder 18)
    Contains bound volume
  - Letterpress Book of Genealogical Correspondence, 1893 (Box 40(B), Folder 19)
    Contains a bound volume in fragile condition
  - Notebooks on Genealogy, including Family Trees, Undated (Box 40(B), Folder 20)
  - Genealogical Notes and Correspondence, 1893, undated (Box 40(B), Folder 21)
  - Genealogical Notes and Correspondence, 1894, undated (Box 40(B), Folder 22)
  - Genealogical Notes, Undated (Box 40(B), Folder 23)
  - Genealogical Notes, Undated (Box 40(B), Folder 24)
  - Genealogical Notes, Undated (Box 40(B), Folder 25)
- Box 41(A), James W. Beekman, Accounts, 1861-1866
  Short description is available in White's guide, Volume 2, pages 302-303. Heavy box filled with misc accounts and receipts.
  - James W. Beekman, Various Accounts, Receipts, Indenture, 1861 (Box 41(A), Folder 1)
  - James W. Beekman, Various Accounts, Receipts, 1862-1863 (Box 41(A), Folder 2)
  - James W. Beekman, Various Accounts, Receipts, 1863 (Box 41(A), Folder 3)
  - James W. Beekman, Bills Paid, Accounts, Receipts, 1864 (Box 41(A), Folder 4)
  - James W. Beekman, Bills Paid, Accounts, Receipts, 1865-1866 (Box 41(A), Folder 5)
- Box 41(B), James W. Beekman, Accounts, 1850-1871
  - James W. Beekman, Various Accounts, 1867 (Box 41(B), Folder 6)
  - James W. Beekman, Various Accounts, 1868-1871 (Box 41(B), Folder 7)
  - James W. Beekman, Cancelled Checks, 1850-1862, 1868 (Box 41(B), Folder 8)
  - James W. Beekman, Correspondence, Accounts, Checks, Large Account With Margaret Milledoler, Marriage Notification James W. Beekman and Abian (Abby) Steele Milledoler, 1840-1860 (Box 41(B), Folder 9)
    Items in folder are not described in White's guide.
- Box 42, Theophilus E. Beekman, 1789-1906
  For more information, see White's guide, Volume 2, pages 439-441.
  - Correspondence, Shares of Stock in Turnpikes, 1809, 1814, 1830, 1845 (Box 42, Folder 1)
  - Theophilus Elsworth Beekman, son of Theophilus Beekman and Elizabeth Matthews, Husband of Maritta Hathway, Papers, Including Purchase Registers, Correspondence, Newspaper Clippings, Undated (Box 42, Folder 2)
  - Theophilus E. Beekman, Correspondence Received, 1813-1828 (Box 42, Folder 3)
  - Theophilus E. Beekman, Correspondence and Legal Papers, 1833-1837 (Box 42, Folder 4)
  - Theophilus E. Beekman, Correspondence and Legal Papers, 1840-1859 (Box 42, Folder 5)
  - Material Concerning the Descendants of Theophilus E. Beekman, Including Inventories and Estate Disposition Materials, 1902-1906 (Box 42, Folder 6(I))
  - Material Concerning the Descendants of Theophilus E. Beekman. Mostly about Estate of T.H. Beekman, Jr, and Marietta Beekman Mundy and Maud Woodhouse, 1866-1905, 1833 (Box 42, Folder 6(II))
  - John Hathaway (Father of Marietta Hathaway, wife of Theophilus E. Beekman) and Hathaway Family Papers, Including Indentures, 1789-1807 (Box 42, Folder 7(I))
  - John Hathaway (Father of Marietta Hathaway, wife of Theophilus E. Beekman) and Hathaway Family Papers, Includes Schoolbook of Arithmetic, 1811-1864 (Box 42, Folder 7(II))
- Box 43(A), Genealogy and Legal Papers, 1700-Circa 1920
  For Genealogy Material, see also Box 12 and 39(A)-40. Some description of this box is in White's guide, pages 372-373. It is not a comprehensive description.
  - Revolutionary Generation Material, Accounts, Correspondence, Chancery Court Record for Abraham Beekman Estate, Newspaper Clipping, Deed, 1703-1810, 1920's (Box 43(A), Folder 1)
  - Genealogy, American Branches, Beekman and Van Dyke Genealogy, 1885-1930 (Box 43(A), Folder 2)
  - Business and Legal Papers, Correspondence, Wills and Death Notices, Maps of Property and Willed Property to Johanna, Catherine, Magdalen, Margaret, Jane, 1770-1820 (Box 43(A), Folder 3)
  - Revolutionary Generation Papers Relating to Carriage, Beekman Arms (hotel), Paintings, Sofa, Documents on "The Cliffs" Long Island Home, Clippings, Circa 1900 (Box 43(A), Folder 4)
  - Revolutionary Generation Wills, Land Papers, Accounts, Taxes, Probate of Will of Rachel Winne, Marriage Certificates, Much on Keteltas Family, 1720-1815 (Box 43(A), Folder 5)
  - Militia Commission to William Beekman, 1746 and 1755 (Box 43(A), Folder 6)
  - Bond Indicating William Beekman's Disposition of Interest in Captured Vessel Brought in by Privateer "William", 1746 (Box 43(A), Folder 7)
  - Gerard G. Beekman, Letterbook (large), 1746-1750 (Box 43(A), Folder 8)
  - Book: American Genealogy, A History of Some of the Early Settlers in N. America and their Descendants, 1848 (Box 43(A), Folder 9)
  - Henry Beekman, Copy re: Patent for Land in Dutchess County, 1924 (Box 43(A), Folder 10)
- Box 43(B), Genealogy and Legal Papers, 1746-1933
  For more description, see White's guide, Volume 2, pages 372 to 373.
  - Gerard Beekman, Diploma from Columbia College and Commencement Address, Focusing on Women's Education and Intellect, 1792 (Box 43(B), Folder 11)
  - Papers of Tarrytown Beekmans, Largely Deeds, War of 1812 Military Appointment, 1746-1812 (Box 43(B), Folder 12)
  - Notes on Boston Newspapers in the Eighteenth Century, Including Stories Relating to William Beekman, Undated (Box 43(B), Folder 13)
  - Revolutionary Generation, Wills and Related Papers, including the estate list of James Beekman, 1833, and Materials relating to the compact wills of William, Catherine, and Mary Beekman, including Conveyances, Probate Materials, and Estate Disposition, 1784-1833 (Box 43(B), Folder 14)
  - Beekman Family Arms, Article in the "New York Genealogical and Biographical Record," Correspondence, 1931-1933, undated (Box 43(B), Folder 15)
  - Genealogy, European Beekmans, Correspondence, Clippings, Notes, 1897-1926, undated (Box 43(B), Folder 16)
  - William Beekman, Letter sent to Brother James and Order for a Keg of Wine "by my Negro man Hanover", August 22, 1780 (Box 43(B), Folder 17)
  - Wilhelmus Baudartius, Autobiography, 1915 (Box 43(B), Folder 18)
  - Account of Beekman Family Bible, 1924 (Box 43(B), Folder 19)
  - William Beekman, Pocket Almanac, Poem of John J. Beekman, 1773, 1911 (Box 43(B), Folder 20)
- Box 44, James W. Beekman, Bulk, 1833-1865; 1796-1909
  For additional information, see White's guide, Volume 2, pages 342 to 367, which contains item-level description of materials in letterbooks.
  - James W. Beekman, Personal Correspondence, Reports for N.S. Milledoler, Introductions, 1833-1874 (Box 44, Folder 1)
  - James W. Beekman, Letter to New York Evening Post, Picture of William Beekman (same image in book in Folder 9), 1908 (Box 44, Folder 2)
    Some material from Folder 2 is described in White's guide, Volume 2, page 369 in "College Notebooks, James W. Beekman."
  - Senator Dixon, Correspondence, Letter from Joseph Francis from St Petersburg, 1859-1860 (Box 44, Folder 3)
  - James W. Beekman, Wills, M. Romero Letter on Death of Lincoln, 1848-1865 (Box 44, Folder 4)
  - James W. Beekman, Taxes, Property Papers and Map, 1861-1866 (Box 44, Folder 5)
  - James W. Beekman, Dutch Reformed Church Affairs and Catalogue of Members, Post Office Land Purchase, Milledoler Will Papers, Accounts, Checks, 1849-1865 (Box 44, Folder 6)
  - James W. Beekman, Business Papers (Including Papers Regarding Sewer on 50th Street), Bonds and Mortgages, Will of Catherine Boudinot (Beekman), Investment in Oil Property, Correspondence, Receipts, 1837-1864 (Box 44, Folder 7)
  - James W. Beekman, Business Agreements, Legal Papers, Property Papers, 1835-1867 (Box 44, Folder 8)
  - The New York Genealogical and Biographical Record Book, January 1909 (Box 44, Folder 9)
  - James W. Beekman, Engravings, Undated (Box 44, Folder 10)
  - Caty Landers and Mary Hamilton, School Notebooks, 1796, Undated (Box 44, Folder 11)
  - James W. Beekman, Gerard Beekman, and James W. Beekman, Jr., College Degrees, Bar Acceptance, 1867-1871 (Box 44, Folder 12)
- Box 45, Memorabilia, 1808-1926
  - "Us," A Book of Poems, Undated (Box 45, Folder 1)
  - General John Steele, Personal and Official Papers (Collector of Customs at Philadelphia, circa 1808-1811). Consists largely of correspondence sent between Philadelphia and Washington City, and contains discussion of the trade embargo., 1808-1864 (Box 45, Folder 2)
  - Benjamin F. Beekman, Draft Copy of Will, 1875 (Box 45, Folder 3)
  - Papers of Intermediate Generation between James and James W. Beekman, Pertaining Largely to Gerard Beekman. Includes Newspaper Clippings, Chancery Court Petition, Correspondence, 1811-1863 (Box 45, Folder 4)
  - Papers of Intermediate Generation between James and James W. Beekman, Regarding Lots #99 and #112 on Broadway and Mercer Street, and Gerard Beekman and Isaac Cox, Including Supreme Court Documentation and Receipts, 1816-1818 (Box 45, Folder 5)
  - James W. Beekman, Columbia College Paper, Correspondence, 1833-1835 (Box 45, Folder 6)
    Potentially detailed in White's guide, page 369.
  - Papers of Intermediate Generation between James and James W. Beekman, Pertaining largely to Gerard Beekman, 1811-1839 (Box 45, Folder 7)
  - Papers, Post James W. Beekman, Including Clippings, Church Bulletins, Correspondence, Genealogy, and Obituaries. Includes Invitation to Dinner with President Teddy Roosevelt at the White House in 1902 and Correspondence with Roosevelt., 1887-1926 (Box 45, Folder 8)
  - Family Scrapbook, Undated (Box 45, Folder 9)
    Bound volume.
- Box 46, Gerard Beekman, Bulk, 1910; 1837-1910
  - Charities of Gerard Beekman, Church Organ Brochures, Documents on Construction of Almshouse "Hall" for Jones Institute, Circa 1910 (Box 46, Folder 1)
  - Charities of Gerard Beekman, "Hall" Construction Documents, Circa 1910 (Box 46, Folder 2)
  - Charities of Gerard Beekman, Correspondence, Rutgers College 150 Yr Anniversary, Church Construction and Repairs, Circa 1910 (Box 46, Folder 3)
  - Charities of Gerard Beekman, Seamen's Church Institute Dedication, Church Repairs and Charitable Giving, Plans for "All Angels Church," Twilight Park, NY., Circa 1910 (Box 46, Folder 4)
  - Gerard Beekman, Plots of Land and Genealogical Notes on William Beekman (18th Century), Documents on Harlem Property including Maps, 1890-1910 (Box 46, Folder 5)
  - Gerard Beekman, Plots of Land Documents in Scotia, NY, Genealogical Notes on Keteltas Family, Circa 1910 (Box 46, Folder 6)
  - Papers and Maps of Real Estate in Upper East Side, 1887, James W. Beekman Death and Supporting Documents, 1837-1839, Undated (Box 46, Folder 7)
  - Photos of Documents for Family Genealogy (mostly 18th-19th centuries) and Herald's College, London, Undated (Box 46, Folder 8)
- Box 47, Beekman Family Oversized Materials, 1781-1925, Undated
  - Beekman and Related Families, Family Trees and Genealogical Notes, Undated (Box 47, Folder 1)
    Previously housed in Beekman Family Box 39
  - Complaint of James Beekman, Jr., regarding the Estate of Lydia Matthews Beekman, 1834; Beekman Coat of Arms, 1834, Undated (Box 47, Folder 2)
    Previously housed in Beekman Family Box 24
  - Beekman Family Account Book, 1781-1783 (Box 47, Folder 3)
    Previously housed in Beekman Family Box 24, Folder 16
  - Survey of Union Cemetery, dated July 6, 1852; Beekman Crest, Original and Copy, 1852, 1925 (Box 47, Folder 4)
    Previously housed in Beekman Family Box 25
  - Agreement for Cemetery Plot for Wilhelmus Beekman and Heirs; Survey of Ten Lots of Land along the East River, from Turtle Bay to Saw Kill, Tracing Ownership to 1676-1677, 1765, Undated (Box 47, Folder 5)
    Previously housed in Beekman Family Box 12
  - Beekman, James, Alphabetical Index of Accounts, Circa 1800 (Box 47, Folder 6)